Harold Foote Gosnell Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Harold Foote Gosnell Papers 1931-1962 (bulk 1937-1959)
MSS49791
Gosnell, Harold Foote, 1896-1997
9,200 items
23 containers
9.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Political scientist, educator, and government consultant. Chiefly subject files consisting of correspondence, memoranda, reports, research data, maps, charts, printed and near-print material, and miscellany. The papers relate principally to projects Gosnell conducted for various government agencies, including a study on state and regional planning for the National Resources Committee; studies on government information services, especially those of the Office of War Information and the Department of State; and analyses of foreign elections for the Central Intelligence Agency, primarily in the Philippines, Indonesia, and the Sudan.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Barnes, Joseph, 1907-1970--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Milton Stover, 1899-1985--Correspondence.; Eliot, Charles W. (Charles William), 1899-1993--Correspondence.; Gosnell, Harold F. (Harold Foote), 1896-1997.
Organizations
United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Department of State.; United States. National Resources Committee.; United States. Office of War Information.
Subjects
Elections--Indonesia.; Elections--Philippines.; Elections--Sudan.; Information services.; Regional planning.
Occupations
Consultants.; Educators.; Political scientists.
Provenance
The papers of Harold Foote Gosnell, political scientist, educator, and government consultant, were given to the Library of Congress by Gosnell in 1976.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library’s Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Harold Foote Gosnell Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Harold Foote Gosnell are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1896, Dec. 24 Born, Lockport, N.Y.
1918 A.B., University of Rochester, Rochester, N.Y.
1922 Ph.D., University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1922 1943 Professor of political science, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1928 Married Florence Lucy Fake (died 1991)
1932 Member, editorial staff, President’s Research Commission on Social Trends
1937 1939 Research consultant, National Resources Committee
1940 Research consultant, Bureau of the Budget
1941 1942 Research consultant, Office of Price Administration
1942 1946 Research consultant, Bureau of the Budget
1946 1950 Research consultant, State Department
1946 1962 Adjunct professor of political science, American University, Washington, D.C.
1950s Research consultant, Central Intelligence Agency
1955 Visiting professor, University of Washington, Seattle, Wash.
1960 1961 Research scientist, Special Operations Research Office
1962 1970 Professor of government, Howard University, Washington, D.C.
1997, Jan. 8 Died, Bethesda, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harold Foote Gosnell (1896-1997) span the years 1931-1962, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1937-1959. The collection consists of files Gosnell compiled as a political scientist and government consultant.
The Gosnell Papers treat four principal topics. The earliest material is devoted mainly to a study Gosnell headed at the National Resources Committee (NRC), later to become the National Resources Planning Board, in which a survey was made of the future of state and regional planning. Contained in the NRC files are reports, questionnaires, research data, and internal memoranda reflecting the agency’s operation. The material represents Gosnell’s own work as well as the research of students, colleagues, and other officials. Correspondence of NRC's executive officer, Charles W. Eliot (1899-1993), the director of the reorganized National Resources Planning Board from 1939 to 1943, appears throughout the files.
A government study of United States information services during World War II, begun by Gosnell about 1943 when he worked for the War Records Section of the Bureau of the Budget, was continued by him at the State Department. At the budget office, the scope of Gosnell’s research was government-wide with a focus on the activities of the Office of War Information (OWI). At the State Department, where he worked from 1946 to the end of the decade, his project was limited specifically to information services in the department itself. Titled “War Information Services,” research files from both projects are topically arranged in one section. Included are memoranda, reports, budget statements, and other documents from government agencies, as well as administrative correspondence relating to planning the research. Subjects treated include the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, the Office of Price Administration, press and media branches of the OWI, State Department and War Department morale programs, and the Experimental Division for the Study of War Time Communications. Correspondents include Joseph Barnes and Milton Eisenhower, former OWI officers who commented on the research while it was in progress.
Other files contain background data and articles Gosnell wrote on the organization of the State Department and source material he compiled while a foreign elections analyst for the Central Intelligence Agency after 1950. His fact-finding missions best documented in the CIA file are trips to the Philippines (1953, 1955), Indonesia (1955), and Sudan (1958). The file contains correspondence, election ephemera, maps (especially from Sudan), summaries of conversations with political leaders and Americans abroad, and related matter.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by topic and thereunder alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- Central Intelligence Agency (Box 1)
  - Foreign political analysis (Box 1)
    - Eastern Europe, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Egypt, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - French parliament, 1951-1962 (Box 1)
    - India, 1948-1962 (Box 1)
    - Indonesia, 1955 elections, 1950-1960, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Indonesia, 1955 elections, 1950-1960, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Japan, 1951-1959 (Box 2)
    - Philippines (Box 2)
      - 1953 elections, 1935-1955, (5 folders) (Box 2)
      - 1953 elections, 1935-1955, (6 folders) (Box 3)
      - 1953 elections, 1935-1955, (4 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1953 elections, 1935-1955, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1955 elections, 1955-1957, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1957 elections (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous elections, 1948-1961 (Box 6)
    - Sudan, 1958 elections, 1956-1960, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Reminiscences of service, 1959, undated (Box 6)
- National Resources Committee (Box 7)
  - Abstracts of dissertations on planning, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., 1938-1941 (Box 7)
  - Administrative aspects of social planning, 1939-1941 (Box 7)
  - Administrative memoranda, 1936-1938 (Box 7)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, newsletters, 1940-1943, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Appraisal of State Planning Board reports, 1936-1937 (Box 7)
  - Appraisal of state and regional planning, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Bibliographies, 1937 (Box 7)
  - City and county planning, 1937 (Box 7)
  - City planning, 1940-1941 (Box 7)
  - Comments on State Planning Board reports, 1937-1938 (Box 8)
  - Conferences, 1938-1939, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence on State Planning Board reports, 1938 (Box 8)
  - Definitions of planning, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Development of planning, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Foreword to State Planning Board report (Box 8)
  - “The Future of State Planning,” 1938, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Housing, 1936-1938 (Box 8)
  - Illinois State Planning Commission, 1935-1939 (Box 9)
  - National Conference on Planning, Minneapolis, Minn., 1938 (Box 9)
  - Notes on State Planning Board report, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Pamphlets, 1933-1939 (Box 9)
  - Personnel directory, 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Planned communities, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Planning “school,” 1938 (Box 9)
  - Population studies, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Procedure for population studies, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Progress of state planning boards, 1938 (Box 10)
  - Regionalism and public administration, 1935-1940 (Box 10)
  - Regional planning, 1937-1941 (Box 10)
  - Report on future state planning, 1938 (Box 10)
  - Simon, Dorothy P., report, 1941 (Box 10)
  - Soviet planning (Box 10)
  - State legislation on planning, 1939 (Box 10)
  - State Planning Board programs, 1938-1939 (Box 10)
  - State Planning Board reports (Box 10)
    - Final tabulations, 1937-1938 (Box 10)
    - Preliminary tabulations, 1937 (Box 11)
  - State planning questionnaire, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Status and summaries of state and regional planning programs, 1938-1939 (Box 11)
  - Status of organizations of planning agencies, 1937-1939 (Box 11)
  - Status of work reports, Charles W. Eliot (1899-1993), 1938-1939, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subdivision control, undated (Box 11)
  - Summary sheets of state planning boards, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Technical committees on national planning, 1938-1940 (Box 11)
  - Technicians Conference, Washington, D.C., 1938, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority report, 1938 (Box 12)
  - Urbanism monograph, 1937-1938 (Box 12)
  - Walker, Robert A., report, 1939 (Box 12)
  - Wehrwein syllabus, 1940 (Box 12)
  - Wisconsin State Planning Board, 1941 (Box 12)
  - Zoning, 1937-1938 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous reference articles, undated (Box 12)
- State Department (Box 13)
  - Office of European Affairs, undated (Box 13)
  - Organization, 1941-1950, (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - Organization, 1941-1950, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - Reorganization Task Force, 1949, (3 folders) (Box 15)
- War information services (Box 15)
  - Appraisals and administrative memoranda regarding history project, 1942-1947 (Box 15)
  - Barnes, Joseph, correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 15)
  - Bibliographies, 1946 (Box 15)
  - Bureau of Overseas Publications, 1942 (Box 15)
  - Coordinator of Information, 1941-1946 (Box 15)
  - Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, 1941-1948, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Domestic information, State Department, 1945-1955 (Box 16)
  - Domestic pamphleteers, 1946 (Box 16)
  - Eisenhower, Milton, correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 16)
  - Experimental Division for the study of War Time Communications, 1941-1943, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1945 (Box 16)
  - Framing the OWI executive order, 1942-1946 (Box 16)
  - History of the State Department, undated (Box 16)
  - International information activities, first phase, State Department, undated (Box 16)
  - Management problems and practices, 1943-1946 (Box 17)
  - Mobilizing for the war of words, 1940-1942 (Box 17)
  - National Security Resources Board, 1949 (Box 17)
  - Navy Department, 1946 (Box 17)
  - News Bureau, Domestic Branch, OWI, 1942-1945 (Box 17)
  - New York Times index on war news and propaganda, 1945 (Box 17)
  - Office of Censorship, 1944-1945 (Box 17)
  - Office of Civilian Defense, 1944 (Box 17)
  - Office of Emergency Management, 1941-1942 (Box 17)
  - Office of Price Administration, 1941-1943, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Office of Price Administration, 1941-1943, (1 folder) (Box 18)
  - Office of War Information (Box 18)
    - Budgets, 1944-1945, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - Estimate of appropriations, 1944 (Box 18)
    - Field information, 1943-1947 (Box 18)
    - Files, 1946-1949 (Box 18)
    - Foreign News Bureau, 1942-1943 (Box 18)
    - History, 1942-1948, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - History, 1942-1948, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - News Bureau, 1942-1943, (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Office of Program Coordination, 1943 (Box 19)
    - Overseas Operations Branch, 1944 (Box 19)
    - Radio Program Bureau (Box 19)
    - Weekly media reports, 1942-1943, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Organization and personnel, State Department (Box 20)
  - Outlines and prospectuses, 1942-1945, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Outposts, 1948 (Box 20)
  - Overhead organization of the OWI, 1942-1946 (Box 20)
  - Overseas Motion Picture Bureau, undated (Box 21)
  - Overseas News and Feature Bureau, 1949 (Box 21)
  - Personnel practices and procedures, 1940-1943 (Box 21)
  - Personnel problems, 1941-1948, (4 folders) (Box 21)
  - Planning and intelligence, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Press and publication activities during the war, State Department, undated (Box 22)
  - Program of the War Records Section, Bureau of the Budget, 1942-1947 (Box 22)
  - Public opinion research in the government, 1946 (Box 22)
  - Recruiting information specialists, 1947 (Box 22)
  - Social Science Research Council, Committee on War Studies, 1943-1946 (Box 22)
  - Transition period, OWI-State Department, undated (Box 22)
  - Transporting the goods, 1945-1946, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - United States at war, 1943-1946, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Warburg, James (“moronic little King” controversy), 1943 (Box 23)
  - War Department (Box 23)
    - Bureau of Public Relations, 1942-1945 (Box 23)
    - Special Services Research Branch, 1943-1945 (Box 23)
- War Production Board, 1944 (Box 23)
- Miscellany, 1931-1959, undated, (5 folders) (Box 23)